Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
Today we take a close
look at a multi-faceted
and often misunderstood
root vegetable.
And we start with a little trick about
lowering their glycemic impact.
If you systematically pull
together all the best studies
on potato consumption
and chronic disease risk,
an association is
found for the risk
of type 2 diabetes
and hypertension.
Yeah, but that was
for French fries.
Consumption of boiled, baked,
or mashed potatoes was not
associated with the risk
of high blood pressure,
but there was still a
pesky link with diabetes.
Overall, potato consumption
is not related to the risk
for many chronic diseases,
but boiled potatoes
could potentially pose a small
increase in risk for diabetes.
That’s one of the reasons
some question whether they should
be counted as vegetables
when you’re trying to reach
your recommended daily servings
of fruits and vegetables.
If you look at other whole
plant foods—nuts, vegetables,
fruits, and legumes (which
are beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils)—
they’re associated with
living a longer life.
Significantly less risk
of dying from cancer,
dying from cardiovascular
diseases like heart attacks,
and 25 percent less
chance of dying prematurely
from all causes put together.
But no such protection
is gained from potatoes
for cancer, heart disease,
or overall mortality.
So, the fact that potatoes
don’t seem to affect mortality
can be seen as a downside.
Now, it’s not like meat,
which may actually
actively shorten your
life, but there may be
an opportunity cost to
eating white potatoes,
since every bite of a
potato is a lost opportunity
to put something even
healthier in your mouth—
something that may
actively make you live longer.
So, potatoes are kind
of a double-edge sword.
The reason that potato
consumption may just have
a neutral impact on
mortality risk is that
all the fiber, vitamin C, and
potassium in white potatoes
might be counterbalanced
by the detrimental effects
of their high glycemic index.
Not only are high glycemic
impact diets robustly
associated with
developing type 2 diabetes,
but current evidence suggests that
this relationship
is cause-and-effect.
A front group for the
potato industry called
the Alliance for Potato
Research and Education
funded a study that found
that intake of non-fried potato
does not affect blood
sugar markers,
but that’s compared with
the likes of Wonder Bread;
so, that isn’t really
saying very much.
Foods with a glycemic
index (GI) above 70
are classiﬁed as high-GI foods,
high glycemic index foods,
and those lower than
55 are low-GI foods.
Pure sugar water, for example,
is often standardized at 100.
White bread and white
potatoes are way up there
as high glycemic index foods.
When you compare them to an
intact grain, like barley groats
(also known as pot barley),
a super-low GI food,
you can see how refined grains
and potatoes are simply no match.
Is there any way we can have
our potatoes and eat them too,
by somehow lowering
their glycemic index?
Well, if you boil potatoes
and then put them
in the fridge to cool, some
of the starch crystallizes
into a form that can no
longer be broken down
by the starch-munching
enzymes in your gut.
However, the amounts of this
so-called resistant starch
that are formed are relatively
small, making it difﬁcult
to recommend cold potatoes
as the solution.
But when put to the test, you
actually see a dramatic drop
in glycemic index in cold
versus hot potatoes.
So, by consuming potatoes
as potato salad, for instance,
you can get nearly a 40 percent
lower glycemic impact.
The chilling effect might,
therefore, also slow the rate
at which the starch is
broken down and absorbed.
So, individuals wishing to
minimize dietary glycemic index
may be advised
to precook potatoes
and consume them
cold or reheated.
The downside of eating potatoes
cold is that they might not
be as satiating as
eating hot potatoes.
But you may get the best
of both worlds by cooling them
then reheating them, which
is exactly what was done
in that famous study I profiled
in my book How Not to Diet.
The single most satiating
food out of the dozens tested
was boiled then cooled
then reheated potatoes.
There’s actually an appetite-
suppressing protein in potatoes
called potato
protease inhibitor II,
but the way you prepare your
potatoes makes a difference.
Both boiled and mashed
potatoes are significantly
more satiating
than French fries.
That was for fried
French fries, though.
What about baked French fries?
Folks had a big drop in
appetite after eating
boiled mashed potatoes, compared
to white rice or white pasta,
which is right where
fried French fries were stuck,
as well as baked French fries.
So, though they may be your BFF,
they’re not very satiating.
In our next story, broccoli,
vinegar, and lemon juice
are put to the test to blunt the
glycemic index of white potatoes.
White potatoes have a high glycemic
index, and consumption
of high glycemic impact foods may
increase the risk of diabetes.
Normally after a meal, we’d
like our blood sugars
to just gently, naturally
rise and fall.
But with high glycemic foods
like potatoes, you get an
exaggerated blood sugar spike
which leads your body
to over-compensate with insulin
forcing your blood sugars
lower than when you started, which
results in negative metabolic
consequences such as a rise in
triglyceride fats in the blood.
However, potatoes are a good
source of potassium, vitamin C,
and polyphenols, which may
counterbalance the glycemic impact.
This may explain why potatoes
appear to have a neutral effect
when it comes to lifespan,
unlike other whole plant foods,
that have been associated
with actively living longer.
In my last video, I detailed
my nip-and-nuke method,
where the act of chilling potatoes
can dramatically lower their
glycemic index, even if you then
reheat them in a microwave.
How else might we reduce the
glycemic impact of white potatoes?
The answer is the same
way you make anything better
in your nutritional
life—add broccoli.
The co-consumption of two
servings of cooked broccoli
with your mashed potatoes
would certainly do it,
immediately cutting the insulin
demand by nearly 40 percent.
In contrast, adding chicken
breast makes things worse
and adding tuna fish makes
things even worse still,
nearly doubling the amount of
insulin your body has to pump out.
Why does plant protein
make things better,
but animal protein
make things worse?
Because decreased consumption
of branched-chain amino acids
improves metabolic health.
I cover this in my book
How Not to Diet as well as
my video on the topic.
Speaking of How Not to Diet,
remember the section on vinegar?
Here are the blood sugar and
insulin spikes someone with
prediabetes can get
from eating a bagel.
Eat that same bagel with
a tablespoon or so
of apple cider vinegar diluted in
about a quarter cup of water,
though, the impact is
significantly less.
Does it work for potatoes too?
Simply chilling potatoes may
cut down on the blood sugar
and insulin spikes, but to
get significant drops in both,
you just have to add about
a tablespoon of vinegar
to drop levels by
30 to 40 percent.
And that was just plain
white distilled vinegar.
Is it the vinegar itself, or
would any acidy condiment do?
In a test tube, lemon juice
appeared to have a remarkable
starch-blocking effect, but
you can’t know if it works
in people, until you...
put it to the test.
And indeed, lemon juice reduces
the glycemic responses to bread.
And not just by a little,
but by like 30 percent.
Now, the subjects were drinking
a half cup of lemon juice,
but that makes it even more
remarkable that it helped because
that added an extra half
teaspoon of sugar,
and yet they still had a
better blood sugar response.
Vinegar is more potent, though.
Just one to two tablespoons a
day of vinegar diluted in water
can significantly improve
both short- and long-term
blood sugar control in diabetics,
which is why clinicians
may want to incorporate
vinegar consumption as part
of their dietary advice for
patients with diabetes.
Finally today, are yellow-
fleshed potatoes
healthier than white?
Let’s find out.
The high glycemic impact of
potatoes may increase the risk
of type 2 diabetes, perhaps by
chronically overstimulating
the insulin-producing
cells in the pancreas.
In my last two videos I
explained how you can decrease
the glycemic impact of white
potatoes by eating them cold,
or chilling then reheating
them, or adding broccoli,
lemon juice, or vinegar.
What else can we do?
Well, if you remember, I had
a video a few years back
that showed how the pigments
in brightly colored berries
can act as starch blockers.
So, if you’re going to eat
a high glycemic food,
you may be able to moderate its
impact by, spreading raspberries
on your toast, for example,
or adding strawberries
to your cornflakes, or sprinkling
blueberries in your pancakes.
No, I’m not saying you have
to put blackberries in your
baked potato, but given
that the natural color compounds
in fruits can slow
down starch digestion,
what about pigmented potatoes.
Even just yellow potatoes like
Yukon gold may be preferable
to white, but the best
may be purple potatoes:
not just purple-skinned potatoes
but purple-fleshed potatoes.
If you’ve never seen purple
potatoes, they are remarkable;
they have almost
a neon blue glow.
And not only do they look
cool, but purple potatoes
cause less of an insulin and
blood sugar spike compared
to even the yellow-fleshed
potatoes, suggesting that
switching from yellow or
white to purple could have
a large potential
public health benefit.
How do we know it’s
the pigments themselves
that are responsible
rather than other differences
between the different potato varieties?
The researchers tried adding a
control comprised of berries in a
potato starch jelly, but that would
seem to add even more variables.
In a test tube, extracts of
purple- and red-fleshed potatoes
can act as starch blockers;
so hey, if you can extract
and purify out the purple-
potato-pigments—
say that five times fast—
you could remove any other
effects of the different
potato varieties by adding the
purple pigments to yellow potatoes.
And low and behold, compared
to just plain yellow potatoes,
you can get a suppression of
the blood sugar and insulin spikes.
This way you don’t get that
overshoot reaction where your
blood sugars can actually
drop below fasting
like you might get otherwise;
instead, you get the gentler
up and down in blood sugars you’d
expect from a lower glycemic food.
The authors suggest purple
potato extracts could be produced
and made into supplements
or fancy functional foods,
but these health-promoting
compounds may be more cost-effectively
received from consuming
purple potatoes themselves.
The Potato Association of
America likes to paint potatoes
as an anti-inflammatory food,
but what they don’t tell you
is that this benefit may be
limited to pigmented potatoes.
If you randomize people to eat
a small white potato every day
for six weeks versus a yellow-
or purple-fleshed potato,
the purple potato group achieved
significantly lower levels
of inflammation compared
to the white potato group,
measuring both c-reactive
protein and interleukin-6.
Pigmented potato consumption
also alters oxidative stress.
Within hours of eating a large
purple potato, you get a nice
60 percent bump in the antioxidant
power of your bloodstream,
and this translates into
less free radical DNA damage.
If you compare the antioxidant
activity of white potatoes,
yellow potatoes, and purple
potatoes, Yukon gold has about
twice the antioxidant power of white,
but purple has twenty
times the antioxidants.
Which is comparable to what
you might see in berries.
Half of purple potato has
about the same polyphenol
antioxidant complement as
half cup of blueberries.
Purple potatoes can increase
the antioxidant capacity
of our blood stream, whereas
straight white potato starch
can act as a pro-oxidant
and decrease it.
Eat a purple potato, and over
the next eight hours the
antioxidant capacity of
your blood stream goes up.
In contrast, if you eat white
potato starch devoid of any pigment,
you can end up worse
off than where you started.
Okay, but does this translate
into different physiological effects?
Yes indeed. Have people eat
either purple potatoes or
white potatoes for two weeks,
and the purple potatoes
improved a measure of
arterial stiffness,
whereas the white potato did not.
And this translates into
a drop in blood pressure,
even in those already taking
high blood pressure drugs,
suggesting purple
potatoes are an effective
blood pressure lowering agent.
But what about the toxic
glycoalkaloid compounds in potatoes?
The toxic human dose starts
around 2-5 mg/kg of body weight,
and the lethal dose is
not too far behind.
But the average amount of total
glycoalkaloids in most potatoes,
however, is less than 100 mg/kg;
so, at the average American
weight of 180 pounds,
a toxic dose is like
four to nine pounds of potatoes.
What happens when you approach that?
It’s possible: nausea,
vomiting, or diarrhea
that could easily be
confused with something like
gastroenteritis or food poisoning.
Some people can start to get sick
at just 1.25 mg/kg of
body weight, or even 1 mg/kg.
That would only be about
two pounds of potatoes
at the average American weight.
It’s also possible they
could start accumulating
if you eat them day
in and day out.
But what about those people
who go on a fad potato diet
and eat three or
four pounds a day?
They can do that without risking
getting sick only if they peel
their potatoes, which removes
nearly all the glycoalkaloids.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.